Wherever, whatever, have a nice day.
My Own Private Idaho is a drama film directed by Gus Van Sant.
In this loose adaptation of Shakespeare's "Henry IV," Mike
Waters is a hustler afflicted with narcolepsy.
Scott Favor is the rebellious son of a mayor.
Together, the two travel from Portland, Oregon to Idaho and finally to the
coast of Italy in a quest to find Mike's estranged mother.
Along the way they turn tricks for money and drugs, eventually attracting
the attention of a wealthy benefactor and sexual deviant.
Mike Waters, played by River Phoenix.
Scott Favor, played by Keanu Reeves.
Richard Waters, played by James Russo.
Bob Pigeon, played by William Richert.
Gary, played by Rodney Harvey.
Carmella, played by Chiara Caselli.
My Own Private Idaho is a 1991 American independent adventure drama film written and directed by Gus Van
Sant, loosely based on William Shakespeare's Henry IV, Part 1; Henry IV, Part 2; and Henry V.
The story follows two friends, Mike Waters and Scott Favor, played by River Phoenix and Keanu Reeves, respectively, as they embark on a journey of
personal discovery that takes them from Portland, Oregon, to Mike's hometown in Idaho, and then to Rome in search of Mike's mother.
My Own Private Idaho had its premiere at the 48th Venice International Film Festival, and received largely positive
reviews from critics, including Roger Ebert and those of The New York Times and Entertainment Weekly.
The film was a moderate financial success, grossing over $8
million, above its estimated budget of $2.5 million.
Phoenix received several awards for his performance in the film, including the Volpi Cup for Best Actor at the 1991 Venice Film
Festival, Best Male Lead from the Independent Spirit Awards, and Best Actor from the National Society of Film Critics.
My Own Private Idaho is considered a landmark film in new queer cinema, an
early 1990s movement in queer-themed independent filmmaking.
Since its release, it has grown in popularity and been deemed a
cult classic, especially among LGBT audiences.
The film is notable for its then-taboo subject matter and avant-garde style.
In 2024, the film was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry by the
Library of Congress as being "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant".
The film explores themes of individual, friendship,
treasure, robbery, sibling relationship.
The tone is emotional.